Guide to the Records of the Office of the Dean, University College of Arts and Pure Science (Francis Hovey Stoddard) 1904-1936 RG.18.0.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Dean, University College of Arts and Pure Science
1904-1936
New York University Archives
Stoddard, Francis Hovey, 1847-1936
RG.18.0.1
2 Linear Feet
Francis Hovey Stoddard was a writer, educator and administrator born in 1847 in Middlebury, Vermont. In 1888 Stoddard came to New York University assuming a position in the newly created Department of English Language and Literature. In 1910 Stoddard was appointed Dean of University College of Arts and Pure Science. He retired from New York University in 1914 and died in New York City in 1936. The records include correspondence, writings and clippings that document Stoddard's tenure at NYU.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Missing Title
General Correspondence
Correspondence (Names)
Subject Files
Related Material at the New York University Archives
The Administrative Papers of Chancellor Henry Mitchell MacCracken, 1884-1910.
The Administrative Papers of Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown, 1900-1937.
The Administrative Papers of University College of Arts and Science/Dean Archibald L. Bouton, 1899-1941.
The Charles Butler Papers, 1817-1908.
Scope and Content Note
This collection reflects the administrative functions of the Office of the Dean of the University College of Arts and Pure Science, filled by Stoddard from 1910-1914. There are also some items relating to his years on the University Senate (1896-1914). These papers document issues being debated at colleges and universities across the nation including; the value of standardization of high school credentials, college entrance requirements, of college-level scholarship and of university standards.
The papers of Francis Hovey Stoddard have been arranged into three series: General Correspondence, Correspondence (Names), and Subject Files. The documents are arranged within the series either by author, institution, recipient of the correspondence, or by subject.
Series I contains letters that document the administrative functions of the Office of the Dean of University College. The issues addressed include faculty hiring, M.A. thesis approval, student records and chapel and class attendance. Aside from the general duties of the office, the papers reflect Stoddard's interest in English language and literature, the standardization of high school credentials, and the University's own admissions, transfer, and degree requirements. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Series II contains Stoddard's correspondence with University personnel, including Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown, Marshall S. Brown (Dean of the Faculties), and John H. MacCracken (Syndic of the University).
Series III focuses on topics and issues of interest to Stoddard and to the Office of the Dean. The files contain correspondence with numerous authors represented in each folder. The material is arranged alphabetically, then chronologically within each folder. Of particular interest are files on the Preparatory Schools Committee that document a program in which faculty visited New York high schools to promote New York University and to recruit students. The New York State Department of Education files illustrate initial efforts of New York State to standardize education.
Biography of Francis Hovey Stoddard
Francis Hovey Stoddard, university educator and administrator, was born on April 25, 1847, in Middlebury, Vermont, the son of Solomon and Francis Elizabeth (Greenwood) Stoddard. Between 1884 and 1886 Stoddard studied English philology at Oxford University, England. In 1869 he earned the A.B. degree from Amherst College. After graduating Stoddard taught in Northampton, Massachusetts, and was later employed in the cotton manufacturing business there. In 1873 he married Lucy Maria Smith of Springfield, Massachusetts. They had one daughter, Lucy. In 1887 he served as Instructor of English at the University of California. In 1888 Stoddard came to New York University and assumed a position in the newly created Department of English Language and Literature. In 1910 Stoddard was appointed Dean of the University College of Arts and Pure Science.
In 1896 he was awarded an honorary Ph.D. degree from Western University of Pennsylvania (now the University of Pittsburgh) and in 1914 an honorary LL.D. degree from New York University. His memberships included the Century Association, the Authors' Club and the American Philological Association. Stoddard retired from New York University in 1914 and died in New York City in 1936.
Francis Stoddard authored many books, including: The Modern Novel (1883), The ideal in Literature (1884), Psycho-Biography (1885), Women in the English Universities (1886), The Caedmon Poems (1887), Conditions of Labor in England (1887), Miracle Plays and Mysteries (1887), Tolstoi and Matthew Arnold (18?), T he uses of Rhetoric: Introductive Work in College Classes (1890), Literary Spirit in the Colleges (1893), The Study of the English Language (1899), The Introduction to the Works of Lord Byron (1899), The Evolution of the English Novel (1900) and Life and Letters of Charles Butler(1903). Stoddard's articles appear in The University Magazine, Inductive Work in College Courses (NYU 1, Series 10). He edited Poems of National Spirit (1904), and contributed to Anglia Enghische Studien, New Englander, Andover Review, Academy and other publications.
In 1886 Stoddard helped found the University Senate and served on that body until his retirement in 1914. Between 1904-1914 Stoddard was Secretary of the Senate and worked on several Senate committees including the Senate Committee for the State of High School Education in the City of New York established in 1898. Stoddard developed a high school visitation program with members of the faculty.
Although Stoddard's tenure as Dean of University College was relatively short he succeeded in substantially reducing the College deficit, established the honors program, initiated the Summer-Spring academic year and examined the issues of standardizing admission credentials and requirements, student conduct, academic scholarship and grades.
Sources:
Annual Reports, 1910-1914. Report of the Dean of the College of Arts and Pure Science.
Chamberlain, Joshua., ed., Universities and Their Sons: New York University. Vol.1 (183- ), Boston: R. Herdon Company, 1901.
Jones, Theodore F., ed., New York University 1832-1932. New York: New York University Press, 1933.
Marquis, Albert Nelson, ed., Who's Who in America. Vol.16. Chicago: A.N. Marquis Company, 1930-1931.
New York University Catalogue, vols. 1888-1914. New York: New York University Press, 1888-1914.
National Encyclopedia of American Business. Vol.XXVII. "A Talk with professor Stoddard. ca.1912. A report by a former student on a visit with Stoddard."
The 20th Century Biographical Dictionary of Notable Americans. University Senate Minutes, 1896-1914.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
Provenance
The administrative records of Francis Hovey Stoddard, 1904-1915, form part of Record Group 18.0.1, Records of the Office of the Dean, University College of Arts and Pure Science. The papers were presumably deposited in the Treasure Room of Memorial Library on the University Heights campus of New York University along with the files of Archibald L. Bouton, who succeeded Stoddard as dean. The records were subsequently transferred to the Washington Square campus following the sale of the University Heights campus in 1972. In October 1977 the University Archives accessioned both the Stoddard and Bouton papers.
Correspondence.; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; Manuscripts for publication.; Clippings (information artifacts); Universities and Colleges -- Admission.; Curriculum planning.; Articles.; Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; New York University. Washington Square College of Arts and Science; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934; New York University. College of Arts and Science; New York University -- History -- 20th century; Snow, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1863-1957
- Series I: General Correspondence
  - General Correspondence: "A-P", 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
  - General Correspondence: "R-Z", 1910-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
- Series II: Correspondence (Names)
  - Bouton, Archibald L., (Professor of English), 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Elmer E., (Chancellor), 1911 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1912 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1914 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Marshall S., (Dean of Faculties), 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fall, Frank A., (Bursar), 1911-1915 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hembdt, Phil H., (English Department), 1913 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hill, Arthur E., (Secretary of the Faculty), 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - MacCracken, John H., (Syndic and Professor), 1910-1914 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - McLouth, Lawrence, (Professor of German Language and Literature), 1912-1914 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Nason, Arthur Huntington, (Professor of English), 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Snow, Charles H., (Dean of School of Applied Science), 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - Admissions Qualifications, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Athletic, 1915-1916 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Athletic Schedules, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Carnegie Foundation, 1910-1914 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Century Club, 1910-1914 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Charts, Statistics on Students, ca.1902-1912 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Discipline, 1912-1914 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Committee on English Requirements, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Student Organization, 1911-1914 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Enrollments, 1911-1913 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Graduate School, 1911-1913 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Medical Preparatory Course, Medical College, 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Minutes and Memos, 1911, 1913, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - New York State Department of Education: School Certification and Admissions Qualifications, 1911-1913 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - New York Department of Education: School Certification and Admissions Qualifications, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ph.D Requirements, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Preparatory Schools, Committee on, 1910-1911 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Preparatory Schools, Committee on, 1911-1912 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Preparatory Schools, Committee on, 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Preparatory Schools, Committee on, 1913-1914 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Prize Scholarship Schools, 1904-1915 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Questionnaires to Freshmen, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Recruitment, 1901-1912 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Report, Analysis of Deficiency (Attendance and Scholarship), 1911-1915 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Report on Course Changes and Requirements, ca.1913 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Report of the Dean of the College of Arts and Pure Science, 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Report [Department of the Interior Bureau of Education Washington], Jun 5, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Report (Scholarship), 1914 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Report, School of Applied Science, 1902, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Report of the Special Committee on for Summer School Work Credit, 1916 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Speeches and Addresses, 1911-1912 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - State Scholarship, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Student Data, 1889-1912 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Student Files, 1910-1913 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Student Hours, 1911-1913 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Student Organization, 1911-1916, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - University and Bellevue Hospital Medical College, Medical Preparatory Course, 1910-1914 (Box 5, Folder 19)